A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - Youth, Series R FA327
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - July 1932 Appeal, 1932-1933 (Box 46, Folder 526)
    Contribution. Income, Cash, and Pledges Receivable Condition Statement of the World Service Committee of the International Committee Three Month Report ending March 31, 1932; 6 pages.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Student Council - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1936-1953 (Box 46, Folder 527)
    Plan of Organiation - National Council, Young Men's Christian Association, June 1949; 1 page.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Maine - Hancock County, 1913-1925 (Box 46, Folder 528)
    The Maine Young Men's Christian Association Reconstruction Foundation Poster.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - New York City - Contributions, 1919-1934 (Box 46, Folder 529)
    Budget Statement: Summary of Operations for Twelve Months Ended December 31, 1928. Branch YMCA STatements. One page.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - New York City - Contributions, 1950-1956 (Box 46, Folder 530)
    Young Men's Christian Association of the City of New York. Balance Sheet, December 31, 1954. One page.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - New York City - Contributions, 1950-1956 (Box 46, Folder 531)
    Exhibit IV: Young Men's Christian Association of the City of New York. Balance Sheet, December 31, 1953. One page.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - New York City - Contributions, 1950-1956 (Box 46, Folder 532)
    Exhibit IV: Young Men's Christian Association of the City of New York. Balance Sheet, December 31, 1952. One page.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Virginia - Norfolk Navy YMCA, 1933-1959 (Box 46, Folder 533)
    1) Letter, July 13, 1936, from A. H. Litchy to Robert W. Gumbel re: sending booklet "Three Stone Steps." 2) Letter, July 2, 1936, from A. H. Litchy to Robert W. Gumbel re: business and will send booklet under separate cover.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Miscellaneous, 1920-1954 (Box 47, Folder 538)
    "The China Weekly Review." "The Story of Shanghai's Foreign Young Men's Christian Association," by George A. Fitch, and related articles. March 24, 1928.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - December 28, 1928 Pledge, 1928-1930 (Box 47, Folder 540)
    1) Exhibit A - Tables of Contribution Income, 1916-1928 2) Exhibit B - Tables of Contribution Income, 1916-1928
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Silver Bay Association, 1904-1958 (Box 47, Folder 541)
    Description of Silver Bay Industrial Institute.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Contributions - Building for Brotherhood, 1957-1961 (Box 47, Folder 542)
    "World Communique," May-June 1958. "Tools for the Task" Issue contains articles focusing mostly on the YMCA buildings of different branches all over the world.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Maine - Bar Harbor, 1933-1949 (Box 47, Folder 543)
    Bar Harbor and Mt. Desert Island YMCA Bank Balance Chart.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Training School - Springfield, 1943-1953 (Box 47, Folder 544)
    Plans for the Laurence Duggett Center, Springfield, Massachusetts. Collins, Willis, Beckonert, Architects, Boston, Massachusetts.
- Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board, 1907-1922 (Box 36, Folder 378)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller contributions; dedication of Laura Spelman Hall; John D. Rockefeller, Sr. contributions. Work in China and South America; post World War I emergency service projects. Labor policy; integration controversy; communism controversy after World War II. Mary French Rockefeller joins National Board; Laurance S. Rockefeller and Mary French Rockefeller contributions to pay for Dodson Study. Correspondents include Mrs. Arthur Anderson, F. J. Haller, Mary French Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel, Arthur Jones.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board, 1928-1949 (Box 36, Folder 379)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board, 1952-1960 (Box 36, Folder 380)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Foreign Division, 1946 (Box 36, Folder 381)
    Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller interest in plans for post-World War II reconstruction of Young Women's Christian Association work abroad.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Membership on National Board, 1915-1927 (Box 36, Folder 382)
    Requirements for membership in Associations and on Board; religious restrictions modified, 1924.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Industrial Problems, 1919-1925 (Box 37, Folder 383)
    Adoption of policy statement regarding role of Young Women's Christian Association in industrial relations between female workers and employers.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Re: Agatha and Ruth Harrison, 1950-1960 (Box 37, Folder 384)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. set up a fund, interest of which was used to supplement income of long-time Young Women's Christian Association worker, Agatha Harrison, and her sister; 1954, Agatha died; biography of her written by sister.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Retirement Fund, 1924-1950 (Box 37, Folder 385)
    Gift by Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial to cover accrued liability feature of National Board's Retirement Fund for Young Women's Christian Association workers. Trevor Arnett's membership on Pension Board. Later additional Rockefeller gifts.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Helen Hughes Memorial, 1920-1923 (Box 37, Folder 386)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to help erect stone chapel honoring Justice Hughes' sister at Silver Bay.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Reconnaissance Study, 1922-1928 (Box 37, Folder 387)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Pledge for Grace H. Dodge Memorial Endowment Fund, 1916-1917 (Box 37, Folder 388)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s $500,000 pledge to the Fund. The money was taken from his Rockefeller Foundation allotment.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Budgets - Statements of Contributions, 1926 (Box 37, Folder 389)
    Summary of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial contributions to National Board and Metropolitan Board.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Budgets - Statements of Contributions - Metropolitan and National, 1922-1924 (Box 37, Folder 390)
    See also Box 46, Folder 534.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Budgets - Statements of Contributions - National Board, 1921-1924 (Box 37, Folder 391)
    Reorganization of Young Women's Christian Association; contributions by Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. letter encouraging Dwight Morrow, Percy Rockefeller, and M. H. Dodge to increase contributions.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - 1920 and 1922 Campaigns - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Letters (Box 37, Folder 392)
    Lists and form letters; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. letters asking others to contribute; donations from Harry F. Sinclair, Col. William B. Thompson; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge. Letters of appeal written by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., A. G. Milbank, Robert W. Gumbel, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - 1920 and 1922 Campaigns - 1920 Campaign Lists and Form Letters, 1920-1922 (Box 37, Folder 393)
    Lists and form letters; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. letters asking others to contribute; donations from Harry F. Sinclair, Col. William B. Thompson; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., A. G. Milbank, Robert W. Gumbel, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - 1920 and 1922 Campaigns - November 1922 Campaign, 1922-1923 (Box 37, Folder 394)
    Lists and form letters; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. letters asking others to contribute; donations from Harry F. Sinclair, Col. William B. Thompson; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. $300,000 pledge. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., A. G. Milbank, Robert W. Gumbel, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Campaign Lists, 1920 (Box 37, Folder 395)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - 1920 Campaign Lists and Form Letters, 1920-1921 (Box 37, Folder 396)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - December 1921 Campaign, 1921-1922 (Box 37, Folder 397)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - 1921-1924 Pledges - March 14, 1921 and June 8, 1921 (Box 37, Folder 398)
    Contributions by Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - 1921-1924 Pledges - March 14, 1922 and June 12, 1922, 1922-1923 (Box 37, Folder 399)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - 1921-1924 Pledges - February 7, 1923 John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Pledge (Box 37, Folder 400)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - 1921-1924 Pledges - February 1924 Gift for National Convention (Box 37, Folder 401)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions
    Contributions by Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller, Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller, David Rockefeller. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions in folders. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Willard S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Frederick T. Gates.
    - YWCA - National Board - Contributions, 1907-1915 (Box 37, Folder 402)
    - YWCA - National Board - Contributions, 1915-1918 (Box 37, Folder 403)
    - YWCA - National Board - Contributions, 1930-1932 (Box 38, Folder 404)
    - YWCA - National Board - Contributions, 1939-1946 (Box 38, Folder 405)
    - YWCA - National Board - Contributions, 1948-1954 (Box 38, Folder 406)
    - YWCA - National Board - Contributions, 1956-1961 (Box 38, Folder 407)
    - YWCA - National Board - Contributions, 1956-1961 (Box 38, Folder 407A)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - June 1, 1931 Gift (Box 38, Folder 408)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - January 6, 1931 Pledge to Unemployment Fund, 1930-1931 (Box 38, Folder 409)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - April 8, 1930 Pledge to Budget, 1930-1931 (Box 38, Folder 410)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - November 19, 1929 Pledge to World's Committee, 1929-1931 (Box 38, Folder 411)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - April 26, 1929 Pledge to Budget, 1928-1930 (Box 38, Folder 412)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - May 3, 1928 Pledge to Budget, 1928-1929 (Box 38, Folder 413)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - April 13, 1927 Pledge to Budget, 1926-1928 (Box 38, Folder 414)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - April 20, 1926 Pledge to Budget, 1925-1926 (Box 38, Folder 415)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - November 19, 1924 Pledge to Budget, 1924-1926 (Box 38, Folder 416)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - February 2, 1924 Pledge to Budget and Deficit, 1924-1926 (Box 38, Folder 417)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - March 1, 1924 Pledge for Japan Buildings Reconstruction, 1924-1928 (Box 38, Folder 418)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - February 1924 Pledge to World's Committee (Box 38, Folder 419)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - January 22, 1924 Pledge for Industrial Work in China, 1924-1925 (Box 38, Folder 420)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Contributions - Greenleigh Study, 1958 (Box 38, Folder 421)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Financial Study, 1921-1922 (Box 39, Folder 422)
    Raymond B. Fosdick suggestions about National Board's financial policy; report of survey of organization by Jones and Fosdick. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Arthur Jones.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Financial Study - May 2, 1923 Pledge, 1920-1927 (Box 39, Folder 423)
    Plans for survey; completion and circulation of report; installation of new finance system. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to pay cost of reorganizing accounting system.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - 1933 and 1934 Budgets, 1933-1934 (Box 39, Folder 424)
    Financial report; Board's needs and activities; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Mabel Cratty Endowment Fund, 1929-1952 (Box 39, Folder 425)
    Plans for raising Endowment Fund; establishment of Trust Fund for benefit of Anna Lyle Cratty; diversion of funds to Board.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Sex Lectures, 1913-1918 (Box 39, Folder 426)
    Report on Young Women's Christian Association sex education; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution for salaries of lecturers and speakers on social hygiene and morality. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Grace H. Dodge, Willard S. Richardson, Charles O. Heydt, J. Greene.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Sex Lectures - Social Morality Work - London / Paris, 1919 (Box 39, Folder 427)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. hoped Royal Commission would be appointed to study Venereal Disease problem.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Centennial Fund
    Presentation of appraisal and plans to raise over $5,000,000 between 1950-1955. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. 1950 contribution to liberalize Pension Fund, $250,000; Mary French Rockefeller acted as General Chairman of Young Women's Christian Association Centennial. 1952 John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gift for endowment of Board, $258,000; 1952 plans for Centennial Observance and Development program. Rockefeller Brothers Fund plans for giving; appeals to Foundations. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. joins sponsoring citizens committee for Centennial Celebration. Mary French Rockefeller's appearance on television show to aid campaign. Gifts by Laurance S. Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller, Nelson Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, Winthrop Rockefeller; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. $500,000 gift, 1955. Success of campaign; plans for use of money. Correspondents include Mrs. A. F. Anderson, Margaret E. Burton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur Jones, Dana S. Creel, Mary French Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    - YWCA - National Board - Centennial Fund, 1950 (Box 39, Folder 428)
    - YWCA - National Board - Centennial Fund, 1951-1954 (Box 39, Folder 429)
    - YWCA - National Board - Centennial Fund, 1951-1954 (Box 39, Folder 0429A)
      Gifts by David Rockefeller. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
    - YWCA - National Board - Centennial Fund, 1955-1956 (Box 39, Folder 430)
    - YWCA - National Board - Centennial Fund, 1955-1956 (Box 39, Folder 0430A)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Centennial Fund - Luncheon, January 11, 1955, 1954-1955 (Box 39, Folder 431)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Martha Baird Rockefeller act as sponsors but do not attend; J. F. Dulles spoke; Laurance S. Rockefeller attended, helped pay costs; Mary French Rockefeller's speech.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - War Work Council, 1917-1920 (Box 39, Folder 432)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller contribution; lease of property from Georgetown University. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1959-1962 (Box 39, Folder 433)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller elected trustee of National Board, 1956; copy of Charter and Bylaws of Board. Gift to Mr. Haller. 1959-1960 analyses of Board's investments; minutes; 1960 revision of bylaws; 1960 financial statement. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel, Matthew G. Ely.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1956-1960 (Box 40, Folder 434)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - National Board - Investments, 1957-1958 (Box 40, Folder 435)
    Suggestions regarding investments; property schedules; investment analyses.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Bar Harbor, Maine, 1908-1944 (Box 40, Folder 436)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts to Young Women's Christian Association for Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; pledges to endowment fund. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, Mrs. D. H. Morris.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Daytona Beach, Florida, 1926-1939 (Box 40, Folder 437)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledge to current expenses; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. final gift. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Robert W. Gumbel, Arthur W. Packard, W. Madison.
    See also Box 46, Folder 535.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Lakewood, New Jersey, 1918-1938 (Box 40, Folder 438)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledges to current expenses; installation of organ from Golf House in Young Women's Christian Association building. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, A. D. Davis.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Jersey City, New Jersey, 1921-1930 (Box 40, Folder 439)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Standard Oil of New Jersey pledges to building fund. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Bayonne, New Jersey, 1926-1954 (Box 40, Folder 440)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution, 1926; later appeals denied. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Mildred Greer, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Cleveland, Ohio, 1900-1935 (Box 40, Folder 441)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Brooklyn, New York - Greenpoint Branch, 1920-1921 (Box 40, Folder 442)
    Standard Oil contributions; gift from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for mortgage indebtedness. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Starr J. Murphy, Herbert L. Pratt.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Brooklyn, New York, 1911-1959 (Box 40, Folder 443)
    1928, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $350,000 to building fund after declining earlier appeals. Later appeals declined. Some material on Queens Young Women's Christian Association needs. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, Mrs. H. A. Ingraham, Thomas B. Appleget.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - Brooklyn, New York - Contributions, 1925-1927 (Box 40, Folder 444)
    Payments of 1925 pledge completed in 1928; contribution for Young Women's Christian Association work with Negros, $500. 1954 $5,000 contribution.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City, 1902-1943 (Box 41, Folder 445)
    Plans for raising endowment fund; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller annual contributions. Litigation between Grace Dodge Hotel and Andrew C. Pollack; material regarding Young Women's Christian Association merger in New York. Declinations of invitations to speak, join boards, etc. Descriptions of projects and programs. 1949, John D. Rockefeller 3rd speech at Campaign meeting; 1952, Winthrop Rockefeller speech at Campaign meeting; contributions by Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Robert W. Gumbel, Mrs. Cleveland Dodge, Arthur W. Packard, Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City, 1944-1947 (Box 41, Folder 446)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City, 1948-1961 (Box 41, Folder 447)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City, 1948-1961 (Box 41, Folder 0447A)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - Beekman Hill Cooperative Association, 1920-1922 (Box 41, Folder 448)
    Copy of constitution and bylaws; property purchases; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution for mortgage on property.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - West Side Branch, 1941-1943 (Box 41, Folder 449)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller membership; reports of branch activities; summary of contributions; work with service personnel.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - February 21, 1919 Pledge (Box 41, Folder 450)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller pledge to purchase land; designation of amount for city work.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - 1920 Campaign (Box 41, Folder 451)
    Lists of men accepting membership on Young Women's Christian Association Advisory Committee; letters thanking John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for talk at luncheon.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - March 6, 1920 Pledge, 1920-1921 (Box 41, Folder 452)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to local and national campaign; other pledges.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - Metropolitan Board, 1921-1924 (Box 41, Folder 453)
    Statement of Budget Fund; summary of joint pledges of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - November 13, 1925 Pledge to Budget, 1925-1926 (Box 41, Folder 454)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - October 30, 1924 Pledge to Budget, 1924-1925 (Box 41, Folder 455)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - December 13, 1923 Pledge to Budget, 1923-1924 (Box 41, Folder 456)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - December 13, 1921 Pledge to Budget, 1921-1922 (Box 41, Folder 457)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - October 28, 1928 Pledge, 1928-1929 (Box 41, Folder 458)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - September 30, 1927 Pledge, 1927-1928 (Box 41, Folder 459)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - November 15, 1926 Pledge to Budget, 1926-1927 (Box 41, Folder 460)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City -1921 Campaign, 1920-1921 (Box 41, Folder 461)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - Studio Club, May 27, 1926 Pledge, 1926-1929 (Box 41, Folder 462)
    Sale of old building; construction, furnishing of new building; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - Contributions, 1912-1917 (Box 41, Folder 463)
    Contributions by various members of the family. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Martha Baird Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - Contributions, 1937-1943 (Box 41, Folder 464)
    See also Box 47, Folder 545.
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - Contributions, 1943-1950 (Box 42, Folder 465)
  - Young Women's Christian Association - New York City - Contributions, 1953-1956 (Box 42, Folder 466)